[Music]
Do you want to finish up talking about
more about cream? Yeah, I would love to.
You have uh more experience with cream
than than I do, so I'd love to hear
about it. Yeah, I think it's it's a it's
a really good point for people to learn
about because and and there's a couple
of nuance things and again I'm going to
give all credit to to my friend Dr. to
Keith Nichols because one thing that
he's been saying for for many years and
that I recently learned about as I was
saying before we've we're just opening a
clinic over here in Latapia and he was
always a real stickler for using one
pharmacy and what you learn is that
differenties even if they have the same
cream base and they're using micronized
testosterone there's a different recipe.
So, it was kind of like if you get, you
know, chocolate chip cookies from 10
different bakeries, they're all going to
be really different just based on how
they make that the cookie. I had no idea
that that's how compounded cream work. I
thought there must be like one universal
recipe that people use. And not only
that, but then the the difference of the
fact that it comes in all these
different
bases, that is a big factor for why
there's so much variance across the
board. Um when it comes to cream and
badly made cream, whether it's like a
commercial preparation with low
bioavailability or um a cream that
isn't, you know, made properly in a
pharmacy, it really doesn't work very
well. But when you get a cream that's
made exceptionally well, which is why
people have to work with, you know,
providers who have a a pharmacy that
they they know and they trust and they
go, "Yep, we send the scripts to this
pharmacy specifically." then you can
have a a really good experience with it.
So, I personally transitioned to cream
when I first moved to well first made
the commitment to move to Lithuania
longterm, which was about a year and a
half ago. And I'd been on uh 250
milligrams per week of testosterone
split over three shots for seven years
or something like that. And because I'd
been stable on it, like I I didn't
really think twice about swapping over.
And I honestly noticed zero change in
terms of my blood work was almost
exactly the same. Symptoms remained the
same. The only thing that changed was I
stopped stabbing myself and started
putting cream on my bulbs. The that's
the only thing that changed for me. So I
became a fan of it just purely out of
convenience in terms of accessibility.
But the thing that I've learned more
over the last year or so in terms of uh
speaking more with with Keith and then
also kind of learning more about what's
going on in theies in the US is this
real preference towards the HRT base of
the cream. And when it comes to topical
medications, you know, the most most
common things in in topical medications
are things like corticosteroid creams or
like antifungal creams. But these bases
that they use for these creams are kind
of universal. So you can kind of put
anything in them and they'll work. But
the HRTbased cream was made specifically
for hormone replacement therapy. And the
thing that I really like about it is
that it's made of olive oil and
macadamia nut oil. So it doesn't have
any chemically smell. It doesn't leave a
residue. And and when you put it on,
it's kind of like putting on like a
really good quality heavy like sunscreen
or moisturizer. So like a full dose for
me, which is 0.5 mil twice a day, that
rivals 250 milligram of of testosterone
per week, is like that much cream. Like
next to nothing. I often say it's about
the same amount of toothpaste you use on
a toothbrush. Yeah. Um,
you know, I I won't put it on my bowls
now for people, but in terms of applying
it, I mean,
if if this was my scrotum here, I mean,
I could pull my pants up now. Like,
that's done. Like, that's that's done.
There's no oil, there's no there's no
smell, there's there's nothing to it.
And, um, the convenience, one, is is is
amazing. But two, the the thing that I
find really beneficial is the the area
that we talked about with guys being
metabolically compromised is a problem.
But the other two challenge areas I see
is one, men with chronic pain, we see an
increase in cortisol, an increase in
prolactin in their blood work and those
two things will drive down five alpha
reductase expression. We also get a lot
of guys who who have the post
finasteride syndrome issue. But the
other issue as well is we get guys who
are on the SSRI anti-depressants and
they're locked into them and all of
these things result in reduced five
alpha reductase activity. So I think
that one of the underdisussed benefits I
mean we know that we get significantly
more exposure to the five alpha
reductase enzyme through the skin. We
put it on the scrotum because it absorbs
with more bioavailability.
But I think one of the other advantages
and this is purely just my theory and
I've spoken to a few people about this
who tend to agree is that when you
inject testosterone the esester is what
gives it that kind of deliberate
bottleneck. So you can get like a
gradual slow release of it over time and
that process happens in in the liver. So
the liver has to cleave the esther off
so the hormone can enter the
bloodstream. So, one thing that I see a
lot in guys who are metabolically
compromised or or drinking too much
alcohol and they need to fix that is is
fatty liver disease. And I do wonder if
all the dysfunction that happens in the
liver with, you know, too much alcohol,
too much body fat, fatty liver disease,
or other medication use, if the liver
functioning suboptimally is potentially
one of the reasons that complicates the
injectable testosterone protocol. And
then when we can bypass that by just
going straight into the bloodstream with
a cream, I do wonder if that could be
part of the reason why these guys don't
get any of the other side effects as
well. Very interesting. Yeah. Very
interesting. And you've you mentioned it
not to under express the importance of
DHT too and the neurosides, right? like
five alpha reductase doesn't just reduce
testosterone, it reduces estradiol,
cortisol, progesterone, all very
important neurosteroids. Um this which
is why nobody should ever use finestide
or dutestasteride but um yeah very
important. So the but the DHT is a very
important neuroststereroid that really
helps with the a lot of the the energy
sense of well-being aspect um which
allows you to do other things like make
your life better. Also, what I wanted to
comment on very interesting is because
this conversation was at the perfect
time because I didn't know much about
the production of creams until recently
when I started to realize that because
I've always had the philosophy I have
partnerships with 12 differenties and
I'll go to whichever one best suits my
my patient. when I started learning that
there is a difference in the bases and
different compoundingies make creams
differently and like you said I've had
reports of people coming back and saying
that their cream was like chalky almost
and dry and I was like what that doesn't
make any sense and then and then I have
a few patients who do better on versa
based cream so I have to give them so
it's like there's a difference and and
some people actually do better on
versabases opposed HRTbased
And so now now it becomes nuanced and
and cream becomes a little bit more
complicated. But but but now that I
understand a little better, I can
actually better ship the clients. But
yeah, you're right. There's a difference
between the compoundingies that make it.
There's a difference between the bases
and it's it's important if you when you
use cream to find the cream that works
the best for you. I've been a fan of the
of the hybrid, right? just because for
some people they they do better on a the
extra DHT conversion and b like the
spikes of testosterone like some people
need to be above a certain threshold of
testosterone
um in order to really have the benefits,
right? And so if I can keep a a base of
testosterone with the injectable and
then allow them to increase on top of
that with with some cream, a we can
reduce the estrogen conversion because
more is converting to DHT and then the
DHT is really beneficial. Um, so I' I've
had a lot of success with with that when
when people have certain conditions. I
think I'm going to steal for obese and
overweight people to really just use the
cream.
We have that policy very much at at at
my clinic where if someone, you know, if
their blood work is severely
metabolically disregulated or their body
fat's particularly high, we just go
look, we can do injections if you really
want, but we really push cream to go
look. And it's it's funny and um you
know, as you know from the space, you
know, patients are never happy no matter
what. But um you get these guys who come
back in who are like, you know, drinking
a bunch, morbidly obese, not exercising.
Like guys who are just like going, "This
is going to be a real trouble case." And
they come back and they go, "I'm sick of
having to shave my balls." I'm like,
"That's the only problem." And they're
like, "Yeah, I'm just sick of it. It's
really annoying." And I'm like I'm like,
"Bro, we just like we just performed a
miracle here." Um, so yeah, it's it and
that that to me always makes me laugh
because I'm going, man, if if this is
the problem people are coming back with,
like this is amazing. You touched on
that before, too, right? Is that like is
is the psyche. And that's a lot what I
have to deal with is is is what we have
to deal with is people's psyche and and
you know, they have high anxiety about
it. So, I've had people just want to
quit testosterone just because of acne.
you you got a few zits and you want to
stop one of the most beneficial
medications in the history of
medications just because you got a few
zits. Like we can control your acne like
like or I've had people say, "Oh, well
my foot started hurting. Should I stop
my testosterone?" Like your foot like
no. Why? That's it's that like people
don't realize. They think a they're on
testosterone so they're going to be like
invincible and just like feel great all
the time. There's like life still gets
in the way. there's still fluctuations
or or people like you like you indicated
before, they'll they'll let these little
things bother them and and everything
becomes testosterone's fault. Like
everything gets blamed on testosterone
and life's still going to happen. You're
still going to get sick. You're still
going to have all these things and and
it's usually not testosterone that
caused all these things. But yeah,
little things like, well, I don't want
to shave my balls, so I guess I'm just
going to quit testosterone. It just
doesn't make any sense. It's it's it's
crazy, man. It's, you know, uh I think
Carl Yung referred to it as um when
people develop neuroticism, which is
kind of like this, you know, snowflake
syndrome where because they become so
stress sensitive because they're so
soft, then these tiny stresses can be
really really problematic. And a lot of
the time when people are really
concerned over these tiny issues, I'm
like I'm like you should be really
grateful that this is your biggest
problem because like other people have
real problems. Um but it it's I think
it's it's a sometimes it can be this
sorry he referred to it as neurosis not
neuroticism neurosis and this this
problem with neurosis that I've seen is
that people and if you just go on Reddit
and look at people's like post history
you can see this perfectly but this
neurosis thing that I've seen is that
people will blame the most recent thing
they did for the problems that they
already had which were often the
problems that led them to taking the
thing in the first place. And um it's it
it's it's you know the classic one is
melatonin. I mean people will take
melatonin. They'll go, "Oh, I stopped
taking melatonin and now I can't sleep."
And I'm like, "It's probably why you
started taking the melatonin." Right. Um
the underlying issues come back. But the
other thing I'll touch on with the
cream, just because I think it's it's
it's worth noting is that um because
everything comes down to, you know,
actual day-to-day logistics with this
stuff. And the this is called a topy
click. And one of the advantages of the
topy click is that you can get these
quarter mil increments whereas the pumps
are locked in a half mil. And the
problem is, and I completely understand
people doing this because I did it, too.
But if you're on cream and you're a new
TRT patient, you're going to go, "Oh,
I'm just going to take a little extra
half pump before I go to the gym." Like,
everyone's going to do it. But the
problem is that it sucks the other half
pump of air back into the dispenser and
it breaks the whole thing. Um, so those
pump packs are really annoying because
one, you're stuck in this half mil dose
increment, but number two, you can break
it really easily. Whereas the other
thing that Keith points out is that you
can put this in any international or
domestic carry-on uh bag on a flight.
Um, no problems at all. they're all the
specific manufacturing of a topic click
is all approved for all the different
regulatory bodies and um I think in
terms of the hybrid protocol so in
Australia we we can never do it because
it's hard enough to prescribe someone
one thing but when I was thinking about
it the other day because my friend Dr.
Eric Serrano is being on the hybrid
protocol as well. He spoke about that at
the Silverback Summit recently. One of
the problems with cream or the
detractions is that, you know, if if you
take a hundred guys and put them on 200
milligrams of testosterone in a week,
you're going to get most guys get about
the same response and then a few
outliers either side, but most people
are relatively clustered around a rough
kind of ballpark. On cream, you get a
lot more of the outliers north and
south. And one of the challenges with
the cream is that even if you get the
best base and you get it made in the
best way, some guys just get a pretty
lackluster response to it. And you can
only I mean it depends on how I guess
big your scrotum is, but you can only
get so much of this stuff on your bowl
sack every 12 hours. I think another
case for the the hybrid protocol is that
if people do want to utilize the more
conversion to DHT benefits of the cream,
but they don't respond to it enough to
use it as monotherapy, then that's where
having an injectable baseline could also
make a lot of sense. But at the same
time, like I've seen guys who get like
one click of this, like half of what I
showed before, will take their
testosterone levels to what an average
guy would get on like 500 milligrams a
week of testosterone. Like the
bioavailability of the HRT base is nuts.
But um you're right, the other one that
works well is the Versa base. Those two
tend to be the the the really popular
ones. And um I think that I tend to
favor the HRT base because we don't have
Versa in Europe, but I know a couple of
doctors in in the US who are who are
like nothing wrong with HRT, but Versa
works really well for them as well. So I
think they're both main thing that guys
can't do is just have an unspecified
generic base because then you're just
going to get, you know, whatever and
that's not going to work. What What do
you think about um application
frequency? Because the the testosterone,
like you said, it's the unsterified
compound. So it's uh absorbs
transdermally is immediately available
for use. Do you like using it twice per
day? Yeah. So there's most of the
studies actually I think all of the
studies on topical are done with a once
daily application and the research shows
that there's a pretty significant peak.
I mean a lot of the time when people
hear that something's on a halflife they
think that it's an even distribution
over the halfife. It's like having a cup
of coffee and going, "Oh, I'm going to
get a 4hour gradual increase in
caffeine."
It doesn't work like that. Exactly. What
we find is the halflife is about 24
hours, but you get a pretty significant
peak before. Once a day is totally okay,
but it's not optimal. So, if people can
only do it once a day, um that is fine,
but twice a day is definitely
preferable. One thing that's interesting
is people will be concerned that the
evening dose will disrupt sleep. I've
only really seen that it helps sleep
because I think we're getting this um
big stress antagonism, you know,
cortisol antagonism. We're getting
adrenaline antagonism. We're getting
people becoming more relaxed from being
in a less stressed metabolic state. And
it's kind of like how T3 before bed can
even help some people sleep as well. But
in practice, the real problem when it
comes to cream application is
transference during intimacy. So the
problem can be, you know, if you sleep
naked with your significant other, that
tiny little bit of testosterone that you
can rub off on her if you if you're
cuddling at night, that can send her
through the sky. Um, so that is
something that people have to be
conscious of, whether it's wearing
underwear or or finding a way around
that. But that's the that's the part
that can be problematic for people is
the the intimacy transference. Yeah.
Okay. Interesting. Have you have you
actually seen that where where females
had a adverse response to to a little
bit of testosterone? Really? Cuz like I
mean just in my mind and this is just a
theory. I've never really like put it
into practice. But you're rubbing that
that much on, you know, well it's it's
just a quarter milligram, right? Or or a
half a milligram on your scrotum. And
then what they're going to be able to
rub off after you've already rubbed it
in. It's such a minute amount. And women
need testosterone anyway. So if they do
rub it a little bit of it, like I
couldn't see it raising it so much that
it that it makes any kind of difference
or or has an adverse, but I don't have
experience with it. So yeah. So, for
example, like of of the same base cream,
a woman's dose, you know, assuming that
she's on like the the female kind of TRT
equivalent thing is usually if a man's
taking 20%, she'll typically be taking
at 2%. So, it's about a tenth of the
dose. Um, I I mean, I've never had it
happen with with my wife or anyone who
I've coached really closely, but I have
seen guys send me their wife's blood
work where their levels are like through
the wazoo. Um, but I I really do think
that it's not a matter of it
transferring via intimacy. It's a matter
of just not washing your hands after you
put it on and and like that kind of
thing. Um, yeah, I think the the amount
that you would even be able to absorb,
you know, from the scrotum, even
sexually, is still quite low. But I
guess it's more so that the risk is
theoretical, but I think it's lower of
the risk that people make it out to be.
But it's just it's the thing that you
just got to be conscious of after you
put it on, you wash your hands really
well and then go on about your day. But
it's um less of an issue than people
think, but it's just it's one of those
things that I guess you have to be
conscious of. Kind of like throwing your
needles, you know. Very interesting.
This has been a great conversation. I've
really appreciated your time. I've
learned a lot. So, this has been
everything that I hoped it would be and
and I think the it'll be everything that
the listeners hop hoped it would be as
well.